ran.org 2019-07-01

# Privacy Policy - Rainforest Action Network

February 12th, 2019

Rainforest Action Network (RAN) is committed to maintaining the privacy of those who visit our websites, [www.ran.org](http://www.ran.org/), [act.ran.org](https://act.ran.org/), [grants.ran.org](https://grants.ran.org/), [japan.ran.org](http://japan.ran.org/), and [forestsandfinance.org](http://forestsandfinance.org/).

RAN is the sole owner of the information collected on this site. This information will not be sold or rented to others in ways different from what is disclosed in this statement. RAN collects information from site visitors at several different points on this website.

We collect only the domain name, but not the e-mail address, of visitors to our website, aggregate information on what pages visitors access, and information volunteered by the visitor (such as survey information, e-mail and other addresses and other personal information).

The information we collect is used to improve the content of our website, to notify visitors about updates to our website, and alert visitors about issues and opportunities. The information is not shared with other organizations for commercial purposes. 

All personal information is stored on secure servers with password protection. Our service providers have privacy policies that also ensure they do not share, sell or rent your information for commercial purposes and that they use appropriate security procedures to protect your data. (NationBuilder – [https://nationbuilder.com/privacy](https://nationbuilder.com/privacy), Blackbaud – <https://www.blackbaud.com/company/privacy-policy/north-america>) Visitors under the age of 13 (US) or 16 (EU & elsewhere), please ask your parent/guardian for their consent before submitting your personal information to this site. If we have reason to believe that someone is underage and we have collected their personal information without proper consent, we will delete that information in a reasonable period of time.

## Financial Transactions

To process a charitable contribution or product purchase, it is necessary for Rainforest Action Network to gather the donor’s name, email address, mailing address, phone, and credit card information. This data is used to verify identity and execute the financial transaction. Additionally, phone number and email address information may be used to contact visitors if there is a problem with the transaction.

RAN may use service providers (such as merchant banks and ecommerce integrators) for the express purpose of conducting financial transactions. It is important to note that credit card numbers are used only at the time of the transaction, and are not stored following the conclusion of the transaction unless a transaction is selected that occurs on a regular basis. For transactions that recur, credit card information is stored in an encrypted format.

Donations to Rainforest Action Network are refundable within 30 days upon written request. If you would like to have your donation refunded, please contact RAN’s Development Department by writing to [membership@ran.org](mailto:membership@ran.org).

## Your Data, Opt Out and Right to be Forgotten

Supporters and donors can write to [membership@ran.org](mailto:membership@ran.org), to obtain details about what information we store about them, to opt out of our list or any sharing services Rainforest Action Network might subscribe to, or to request changes to his or her personal data as collected by Rainforest Action Network.

Supporters and donors have the “Right to be Forgotten” and can write to [membership@ran.org](mailto:membership@ran.org) to request that all their personal data as collected by RAN be removed from all our records.

RAN and our agents will notify authorities within 72 hours in case of any data breaches.

## Electronic Newsletter

If a site visitor chooses to subscribe to any of our electronic newsletters through the sign-up forms on our site or while making a donation, RAN requests contact information such as name and email address.

This information is stored securely with a third-party service provider (our agent) for the sole use of RAN. We do not share this information with any third-party but we sometimes send messages to our supporters asking them to take action with our partner organizations. Supporters are encouraged to read the privacy statements of each and every website that collects personally identifiable information from them.

## Cookies Policy

Rainforest Action Network uses cookies on all our websites. By using our websites you consent to the use of cookies.

Cookies are small pieces of text sent to your web browser by a website you visit. A cookie file is stored in your web browser and allows the website or a third­-party to recognize you and make your next visit easier and more useful to you.

When you use and access our website we may place a number of cookies files in your web browser.

We use cookies for the following purposes: to enable certain essential functions of our websites, to provide analytics, to store your preferences and improve your experience, and to enable us to reach you on social media platforms.

We use both session and persistent cookies on our websites. We use essential cookies to authenticate users and prevent fraudulent use of user accounts. In addition to our own cookies, we use various third-­party’s cookies to report website usage statistics, and track the effectiveness of our web based advertising.

## Action Center

RAN provides an advocacy service allowing site visitors to contact corporate leaders, key members in the business community and other members of the private sector on issues of concern. Contact information such as name and email address are requested. If cookies are enabled on a visitor’s computer, then our site will use cookies to identify previous users of our advocacy service to enhance their experience.

## Links

RAN provides links to other websites. RAN is not responsible for the privacy practices of such other sites. Site visitors are encouraged to be aware when they leave our websites and to read the privacy statements of each and every website that collects personally identifiable information. This privacy statement applies solely to information collected by our websites.

## Changes to this policy

RAN reserves the right, in its sole discretion and without any obligation, to modify or correct any errors or omissions in any portion of this website. If our information practices change at some time in the future we will post the policy changes to our website to notify you of these changes and provide you with the ability to opt out of these new uses. If you are concerned about how your information is used, you should check back at our website periodically.

## Contact Us

For questions: regarding this policy statement, the practices of this site, if you feel that this site is not following its stated information policy, or to review or request changes to your contact information, you may contact us at [membership@ran.org](mailto:membership@ran.org). To opt-out of receiving any of our communications or messages we share for partner organizations please write in to membership@ran.org with your specific request.
